## Thomas Shull

Hardstrasse 201 Floor 17, 8005 Zürich CH, email: mail@tomshull.com, mobile: +41-77-267-56-74, thomasshull.net

Research Interests Hardware and software designs to improve the execution of managed languages. Profiling-based compiler optimizations. Techniques to reduce the overhead of automatic memory management. Interprocedural analysis. Techniques for code-size reductions.

**EDUCATION** 

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

August 2012 - August 2020

Ph.D. in Computer Science Advisor: Prof. Josep Torrellas

**Thesis**: Making Non-Volatile Memory Programmable

Committee: Prof. Josep Torrellas, Prof. Jian Huang, Prof. David Padua, Prof. James Larus,

and Prof. Steven Swanson

Washington University of St. Louis

June 2008 - May 2012

B.Sc. in Computer Science and B.Sc. in Computer Engineering

Summa Cum Laude

Professional EXPERIENCE

Oracle Labs

June 2020 – Present

Principal Researcher on GraalVM Project

Core developer on GraalVM Native Image team. Also primary maintainer of GraalVM's AArch64 backend. GraalVM Native Image is a framework and runtime environment for the ahead-of-time compilation of Java applications. GraalVM is Oracle's next generation compiler, runtime, and language development environment to improve both the developer experience and performance.

Arm Ltd.

July 2019 – April 2020

Open Source Software

Worked on AArch64 port of GraalVM. Made multiple bug fixes and performance improvements, including adding support for AArch64 runtime code installation.

Non-Volatile Memory Research

Proposed ISA extensions to improve crash-consistent application performance by enabling more aggressive instruction reordering; implemented extensions within gem5 simulator. Also improved and fixed the AArch64 port of the Persistent Memory Development Kit.

SELECTED **PUBLICATIONS**  Execution Dependence Extension (EDE): ISA Support for Eliminating Fences (ISCA 2021), Thomas Shull, Ilias Vouqioukas, Nikos Nikoleris, Wendy Elsasser, and Josep Torrellas

AutoPersist: An Easy-To-Use Java NVM Framework Based on Reachability (PLDI 2019), Thomas Shull, Jian Huang, and Josep Torrellas

Reusable Inline Caching for JavaScript Performance (PLDI 2019), Jiho Choi, Thomas Shull, and Josep Torrellas

QuickCheck: Using Speculation to Reduce the Overhead of Checks in NVM Frameworks (VEE 2019), Thomas Shull, Jian Huang, and Josep Torrellas

NoMap: Speeding-Up JavaScript Using Hardware Transactional Memory (HPCA 2019), Thomas Shull, Jiho Choi, María J. Garzarán, and Josep Torrellas

Biased Reference Counting: Minimizing Atomic Operations in Garbage Collection (PACT 2018), Jiho Choi, Thomas Shull, and Josep Torrellas

Defining a High-level Programming Model for Emerging NVRAM Technologies (ManLang 2018), Thomas Shull, Jian Huang, and Josep Torrellas

ShortCut: Architectural Support for Fast Object Access in Scripting Languages (ISCA 2017), Jiho Choi, **Thomas Shull**, and Josep Torrellas

Improving JavaScript Performance by Deconstructing the Type System (PLDI 2014), Wonsun Ahn, Jiho Choi, Thomas Shull, María J. Garzarán, and Josep Torrellas

TECHNICAL SKILLS Programming Skills: C/C++, Java, Python.

Managed Language Implementations: GraalVM Native Image, OpenJDK

Compiler Implementations: Graal, HotSpot (C1 & C2), LLVM

References

Christian Wimmer, christian.wimmer.priv@gmail.com formerly GraalVM technical lead Josep Torrellas, torrella@illinois.edu University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Stuart Monteith, stuart.monteith@arm.com Arm Ltd. Additional references available upon request